Guide to the Coudert, Frederic R., Jr. Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Frederic René Coudert, Jr., Papers
1923-1975.
Coudert, Frederic René, 1898-1972.
44 linear ft. (87 document boxes & 1 oversize folder).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0290
4078447
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, documents, and printed materials of the noted lawyer and Congressional Representative, Frederic René Coudert, Jr.
Biographical Note
Congressional Representative from New York; born in New York City May 7, 1898; attended Browning and Morristown Schools in New York City; was graduated from Columbia University in 1918 and from its law school in 1922 [Kent Scholar]; served as a first lieutenant in the One Hundred and Fifth United States Infantry, Twenty-seventh Division, with overseas service, in 1917 and 1918; was admitted to the bar in 1923 and commenced practice in New York City; assistant United States attorney for the southern district of New York in 1924 and 1925; unsuccessful Republican candidate for district attorney of New York County in 1929; delegate to the Republican State conventions from 1930 to 1948; delegate to the Republican National Conventions 1936-1948; member of the State Senate, 17th district, 1939-1946; elected as a Republican to the Eightieth and to the five succeeding Congresses (January 3, 1947-January 3, 1959); Chairman of the Rapp-Coudert Subcommittee; was not a candidate for renomination in 1958 to the Eighty-sixth Congress; engaged in the practice of law in New York City; member of State Commission on Governmental Operations of the city of New York 1959-1961; retired from the practice of law due to ill health and resided in New York City, where he died May 21, 1972; interment in Memorial Cemetery, Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, and printed materials. There is correspondence relating to Coudert's law practice, political campaigns, and terms in office. Correspondence, subject files, press releases, and clippings concerning Coudert's state senatorial and U.S. congressional campaigns, and his involvement in the New York State Joint Legislative Committee on the State Education System (Rapp-Coudert Committee, 1940-46), as well as the New York State Commission on Governmental Operations of the City of New York (1959-61). The scrapbooks contain clippings on Coudert's political career from 1929 through 1962, the Jones Law and the Rapp-Coudert Subcommittee.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Catalogued and Arranged Correspondence
Series II: General Political Correspondence
Series III: Subject Files
Series IV: Scrapbooks
Series V: Oversized
Subjects
New York (State).--Commission on Governmental Operations in the City of New York.; United States.--Congress.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; New York (State)--Joint Legislative Committee on the State Education System.; Appointments.; Bills (legislative).; Budgets.; Financial records.; Minutes.; Photoprints.; Posters.; Press releases.; Scrapbooks; Lawyers.
Acquisition
09/27/87 M-87-09-28 Coudert, Paula M. Gift
Bequest of Pamela M. Coudert, 1986 & 1987.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 2-87. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Catalogued and Arranged Correspondence
  - Aldrich, Winthrop W. (Box 1)
  - Altschul, Frank (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish (Box 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray (Box 1)
  - Davis, Gherardi (Box 1)
  - Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edward) (Box 1)
  - Dirksen, Everett McKinley (Box 1)
  - Dulles, John Foster (Box 1)
  - Gildersleeve, Virginia Crocheron (Box 1)
  - Hoover, Herbert (Box 1)
  - Javits, Jacob J. (Box 1)
  - Kirk, Grayson (Box 1)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot (Box 1)
  - MacLeish, Archibald (Box 1)
  - Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous) (Box 1)
  - Olcott, J. van Vechten (Jacob van Vechten) (Box 1)
  - Peale, Norman Vincent (Box 1)
  - Rickenbacker, Eddie (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (Box 1)
  - Smith, Margaret Chase (Box 1)
  - Stassen, Harold Edward (Box 1)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays (Box 1)
  - Wardwell, Allen (Box 1)
- Series II: General Political Correspondence
  - 1940-1945 A-C (Box 1)
  - 1940-1945 D-M (Box 2)
  - 1940-1945 N-Z (Box 3)
  - 1947-1948 A-Z (Box 4)
  - 1949-1956 A-F (Box 4)
  - 1949-1956 G-Z (Box 5)
  - 1957-1970 A-Z (Box 6)
- Series III: Subject Files
  - 1929 Campaign for District Attorney:
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Coudert's platform (Box 7)
    - Article by Coudert for NYU Law Review (Box 7)
    - 1929 Jones Law (Box 8)
    - 1932-1934 Committee for the Consideration of International Debts (Box 8)
    - 1939 N.Y. State World's Fair Commission (Box 9)
  - 1940 State Senatorial Campaign: (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Address Lists (Box 10)
    - Campaign Material File (Box 10)
    - Misc. Papers and Materials (Box 10)
    - Press Statements (Box 10)
    - Vote in the 10th, 15th and 17th Assembly Districts (Box 10)
  - 1942 State Senatorial Campaign:
    - Address Lists (Box 11)
    - Bills, Advertising, Literature (Box 11)
    - Campaign Material to Defeat Coudert (Box 11)
    - Citizens for Coudert Committee (Box 11)
    - Contributions (Box 11)
    - Correspondence re. Campaign (Box 11)
    - Letters on Behalf of Coudert (Box 11)
    - Material File (Box 11)
  - 1944 State Senatorial Campaign: (Box 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 12)
    - Clippings (Box 12)
    - Material File (Box 12)
  - 1946 Correspondence re. bills introduced by Coudert in 1946 (Box 12)
  - 1939-1946 Miscellaneous State Senatorial Files: (Box 13)
    - Anti-Discrimation Bill--Clippings (Box 13)
    - J.A. Arnold--Western Tax Council (Box 13)
    - Correspondence for Senate Clerk W.S. King (Box 13)
    - Legislative Speeches, 1939-1940 (Box 13)
    - Multiple Dwelling Law (Box 13)
    - Remarks on Debates (Box 13)
    - Stock Exchange Taxes (Box 13)
    - Stockholders' Derivative Actions (Box 13)
    - Teachers' Retirement Bill (Box 13)
    - Transit Unification (Box 13)
  - 1940-1946 Rapp-Coudert Legislative Committee to Investigate the Public (Box 14)
  - Educational System--Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 14)
  - 1940-1946 Rapp-Coudert Legislative Committee to Investigate the Public (Box 15)
  - Educational System--Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 15)
  - "The Communist Youth Movement." Typed manuscript (Box 16)
  - Legal Proceedings (Box 16)
  - Page 6 of 10 Frederic René Coudert, Jr., Papers (Box 16)
  - B.V. Dodd and R.K. Spear vs. Knicherbocker Broadcasting Co., Bud (Box 16)
  - Roth, Joint Legislative Committee (Box 16)
  - Memoranda (Box 16)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Report of Survey Staff; February 1, 1944 Vol. III Colleges (Box 16)
  - Reports (Box 16)
  - Resolutions (Box 16)
  - Clippings (Box 16)
  - George Britt's Clippings (Box 16)
  - "Subversive Activities" [clippings] (Box 16)
  - Committee Press Releases (Box 16)
  - Communist Press Releases (Box 16)
  - Printed Materials (Box 17)
  - 1946-1958 U.S. Congressional Career:
    - 1946 Congressional Campaign (Box 18)
    - Correspondence (Box 19)
    - Address Lists (Box 19)
    - Campaign Expenditures (Box 19)
    - Canvassing File (Box 19)
    - Captain's Reports and Files (Box 20)
    - Contributions (Box 20)
    - Material File (Box 20)
    - Material to Defeat Senator Coudert (Box 20)
    - Press Releases (Box 20)
    - Representative Baldwin (Box 20)
    - Representative Marcantonio (Box 20)
    - Tool Owners' Questionnaire (Box 20)
  - Clippings (Box 21-22)
  - 1947-1948 Bills introduced by Coudert to 80th Congress (Box 23)
  - 1948 Congressional Campaign: (Box 24)
    - Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Clippings (Box 24)
    - Financial Reports (Box 24)
    - Material File (Box 24)
  - 1949-1950 Bills introduced by Coudert to 81st Congress (Box 25)
  - 1950 Congressional Campaign:
    - Correspondence (Box 26)
    - Atlantic Union Resolution (Box 26)
    - Expenditure Receipts (Box 26)
    - Material File (Box 26)
    - Material to Defeat Coudert (Box 27)
    - Press Releases (Box 27)
    - World Federalists File (Box 27)
    - Clippings (Box 27)
  - 1951-1952 Bills introduced by Coudert to 82nd Congress (Box 28)
  - 1952 Congressional Campaign Primary: (Box 29)
    - Correspondence (Box 29)
    - Material File (Box 29)
    - Material to Defeat Coudert (Box 29)
    - Memoranda File (Box 29)
    - Press Releases (Box 29)
    - Proposed Statements (Box 29)
  - 1952 Congressional Campaign: (Box 30)
    - Correspondence (Box 30)
    - Campaign Reports (Box 30)
    - Material File (Box 30)
    - Material to Defeat Coudert (Box 30)
    - Clippings (Box 31)
  - 1954 Congressional Campaign:
    - Correspondence (Box 32)
    - Material File (Box 32)
    - Material File (Box 33)
    - Material to Defeat Coudert (Box 33)
    - Reports File (Box 33)
    - Working File (Box 33)
    - Clippings (Box 33)
  - 1955-1956 Bills introduced by Coudert to 84th Congress (Box 34-35)
  - 1956 Congressional Campaign:
    - Correspondence A-Z (Box 36-37)
    - Campaign Expenditures (Box 38)
    - Draft Statements (Box 38)
    - Material File (Box 38)
    - Photographs (Box 38)
    - Press Releases (Box 38)
    - Clippings (Box 39)
  - 1956 Davis Congressional Investigation (Box 40)
  - 1957-1958 Bills introduced by Coudert to 85th Congress (Box 41-43)
  - 1958 Congressional Campaign:
    - Campaign Polls (Box 44)
    - Goodwin Material (Box 44)
    - Material to Defeat Lindsay (Box 44)
    - Material File (Box 44)
    - Clippings (Box 44)
  - 1959-1961 New York State Commission on Government Operations:
    - Correspondence (Box 45)
    - City Councils (Box 45)
    - Classification of Licenses (Box 45)
    - Critical Material (Box 45)
    - Data re Borough President (Box 45)
    - Debt Management (Box 45)
    - Drafts and Reports (Box 46)
    - Expense Budget (Box 46)
    - Financing of Local Programs (Box 46)
    - Hearings (Box 46)
    - Highway Maintenance (Box 46)
    - Incumbrances Plan (Box 46)
    - Luther Gulick Memo (Box 46)
    - The Mayor and his Office (Box 47)
    - Memoranda (Box 47)
    - Minutes of Meetings (Box 47)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 47)
    - Sewer Maintenance (Box 48)
    - Tax Foundation Material (Box 48)
    - Traffic Direction (Box 48)
    - Photographs (Box 48)
    - Clippings (Box 48)
  - "Background Research on the Top Structure of the Government of the city of New York" (Box 49)
  - Miscellaneous Subject Files: (Box 50)
    - American Society of the French Legion of Honor (Box 50)
    - Appointments to Annapolis (Box 50)
    - Appointments to King's Point (Box 50)
    - Appointments to West Point (Box 50)
    - Coudert Book (Box 50)
    - Vichy Politics (Box 50)
    - Clippings (Box 50)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks
  - 1929 Campaign for New York County District Attorney [scrapbooks 1-11] (Box 51-54)
  - Jones' Law (Prohibition) [scrapbooks 12-13] (Box 54-55)
  - Prohibition, 1930-1933 [scrapbook 14] (Box 55)
  - Senatorial Campaign, 1938 [scrapbook 15] (Box 56)
  - Joint Legislative Committee Investigation Hearings [scrapbook 16] (Box 56)
  - New York State Legislature, 1938-1943 [scrapbooks 17-31] (Box 57-63)
  - Miscellaneous and Personal [scrapbooks 31-39] (Box 64-68)
  - Special Clippings [scrapbooks 40-41] (Box 68)
  - Rapp-Coudert Committee [scrapbooks 42-52] (Box 69-74)
  - Political Clippings, 1940-1961 [scrapbooks 53-63] (Box 75-80)
  - Congressional Clippings, 1947-1962 [scrapbooks 64-77] (Box 80-87)
- Series V: Oversized
  - Coudert, Jr. Campaign Posters